"Qiu Yuan's Old Words"
《邱元旧言》
Qiu Yuan's old words, hello, everyone
邱元旧言 各位觀眾大家好
The guards of our hospital commemorate the 130th birthday of Mr. Hu Shi, President Gu
本院衛紀念顧院長胡適先生130歲名誕
Specially hold a feast of knowledge this month
特別以本月舉辦知識饗宴
The speakers invited by President Hu Shi for the popular science lectures are
胡適院長科普講座邀請到的講者為
Winner of Hu Shi Memorial Research Lecture in 1909
1909年胡適紀念研究獎座德獎人
Qiu Zhonglin, a researcher at the Institute of History of our school
本院歷史研究所邱仲林研究員
Lecture for us on the history of hoarding and cutting money in Chinese history
為我們主講精囤割錢中國歷史上的歷史
Researcher Qiu Zhonglin was a postdoctoral fellow at the Institute of History, National Taiwan University in 1997
邱仲林研究員於1997年或臺灣大學歷史學研究所博士後
Said a teacher in the History Department of Danjiang University
稱一丹江大學歷史學系擔任教師
Since 2001, he has been working as a research officer in 11 institutes of our hospital
自2001年起進入本院11所從事研究官
work so far
工作至今
He was awarded the 2006
他成獲2006年本院
Research Writing Award for Young Scholars
年輕學者研究著作獎
Ministry of Science and Technology 2018
科技部2018年度
Outstanding Research Award
傑出研究獎
And last year with a festival ceremony to mobilize
並於去年以節日儀式以動員
A research project centered on the official village camp activities of the Youth League
以民青官方的營村活動為中心研究計畫
Won the Hu Shih Memorial Research Award
獲本院胡適紀念研究獎座
Researcher Qiu has long been committed to the social and cultural history of the Minqing Youth League
邱研究員長期致力於民青社會文化史
and Material Culture Studies
及物質文化研究
Talking about the topic
主題多言
Includes blue material drainage medical system
包括藍料排水醫療制度
spending history
花費史
in Chinese history
以中國歷史上
Good at separating records, etc.
精於隔遣的紀錄等等
In the near future, it focuses on the military epidemic prevention system of the Ming Dynasty
近期則關注明代軍事防疫體系
and long-distance travel history
及長途旅行史等議題
Today he will share with us
今天他將與我們分享
The record of collective segregation in the history of China
中國歷史上精囤集體隔遣的紀錄
And examine the cultural explanations of the ancients for this phenomenon
並考察古人對此現象的文化解釋
Listen carefully to the wonderful and promising background content
以背景內容精彩可期之的大家仔細聆聽
Welcome to Researcher Qiu Zhonglin
歡迎邱仲林研究員
Dean of Defense, Hello, audience.
防務院長各位觀眾大家好
It is a great honor to be invited by the academy to give a lecture today
今天非常榮幸受院裡面邀請來做一個講座
The topic I'm going to talk about has been reported by the chief of defense.
我要講的這個題目防務院長已經報告了
I'll just start talking
我就直接開始講
Research on this topic actually collected materials very early
研究這個題目其實收集的材料非常的早
generally speaking
一般來講就是說
There are very scattered records about money cutting in Jintun in Chinese history
有關於中國史上金屯割錢的記載非常淋散
Distributed in history books, local characters and some notes
分佈在史書還有地方字還有一些筆記裡面
The time span is relatively long, starting from the Han Dynasty
那時間的跨度也比較久從漢代
until contemporary
一直到當代
presumably can be disconnected probably in 1949
大概可以斷線大概是在1949年
Because this after 1949
因為1949年以後的這個
Many newspapers and periodicals are actually in mainland China
報刊很多其實都在大陸
i can't collect
我沒辦法收集到
So basically I probably won't discuss
所以基本上我大概就不討論
There are records about this
有關於這方面的記載
let's start now
我們現在開始來看
purpose of this study
這個研究的目的
mainly through data analysis
主要是要透過資料分析
The natural history of fine hoarding
精囤的自然史
With this space-time background stranded with it
跟它擱淺的這個時空背景
The reason for the shallow cut and the cultural explanation
那割淺的原因跟文化解釋
is also the part I'm going to discuss
也是我要討論的這個部分
But it's a pity
但是比較可惜就是
Written Records of Chinese Social Pollutants and Governance
中國社會染治方面的文字記載
Relatively probably a little more than the West and Japan
相對可能比西方還有日本多一點
But there is very little image data
但是圖像資料非常的缺乏
And even with this profile of this image
而且即使有這個圖像的這個資料
It draws this fine and shallow look
它畫的這個精囤割淺的這個樣子
also very ridiculous
也非常的可笑
You can read from that poster
大家可以從那個海報上面
can be seen
可以看出來
The one on the seal is basically from the late Qing Dynasty
海豹那一張基本上是晚清的
"Time is in the pictorial"
《點時在畫報》
A picture drawn of Jintun Shallow
所畫的一張金屯隔淺的圖
But he drew the goldfish to look like a carp
可是他把金魚畫成很像鯉魚
It also represents our traditional literati
也就代表我們傳統的文人
I'm drawing this about the sea
在畫這個有關於海上的
Huge catch-like animals when
巨大的捕捉類動物的時候
their understanding
他們的理解認為
He and these fishes inland
他跟內陸上面的這些魚類
almost the same
相差不多
From this perspective
從這個角度看
In fact, far behind
其實遠遠落後
Japan and the West
以日本跟西方
We'll see a picture later
待會我們會看一張圖
That's a picture of the West
那個是西方的圖
in Chinese history
在中國史上面
Crunchy Jintun shallow record
脆脆的金屯隔淺的紀錄
probably belong to the two sides
大概是屬於這個兩岸
in 16 BC
西元前16年的時候
In the place Beihaijun in Shandong
在山東的北海峻這個地方
Once there was a big fish shallow
曾經出現一條大魚隔淺
on this coast
在這個海岸
Six long and one tall, there are four in total
長六張 那高一張 總共有四條
Then in 4 BC, probably in Donglai County, Shandong
接著在西元前四年 大概在山東東來郡
There is also Lantau cutting money in Pingdu
平渡這個地方也有大嶼割錢
There are seven in total, all dead.
總共有七條 都已經死了
In AD 173 also in Donglai County
在西元173年的時候 同樣在東來郡
The sea pushed two more Lantaus onto the coast
海面上又把兩條大嶼推到海岸上
Its length is eight or nine sheets, and its height is about one sheet.
它的長度都是八九張 高大概一張多
The terms used by the two sides of the Taiwan Strait to cut money from Jinyintun
兩岸對於金銀屯割錢所用的字眼
In fact, until now, especially in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
其實到現在的 特別是到明清
Even in modern times, some people are saying that this phenomenon is called sea pig Lantau
甚至到現代 有人在說這種現象叫做海豬大嶼
It refers to gold and copper cutting money
它指的就是金銅割錢
I just said that this is a plate of Henan in the West
剛剛講說這個是西方的一個河南的板化
We drew this goldfish cutting pliers
我們畫的這個金魚割鉗
That's a pair of incense-smeared gold cutting pliers
就是這是一條抹香金割鉗
it's very realistic
它非常的寫實
Even its genitals are drawn
甚至包括它的生殖器都會畫出來
And it can be seen from the ratio of it to people.
還有它跟人的比例大概也可以看出來
But we in China are very short of such image materials
可是我們中國就很缺乏這種圖像的材料
And the director of the painting is very wrong
而且畫的廠長都是誤差很大
it's a pity
這比較可惜
On the Japanese side, in fact, because of their tradition
日本方面其實他們因為傳統以來
The supplementary gold industry is very developed
補金業非常發達
So they were in the 17th and 18th centuries
所以他們在17、18世紀
There are also many pictures of this kind of supplementary money left behind.
也留下來很多這種補金的圖
Images of various types of gold painted inside
裡面所畫的關於各種金類的圖像
are also very accurate
也都非常精準
China may have entered the sea in the long-term Ming and Qing Dynasties
中國可能跟長期明清時期海進
And the message to the ocean is not that big
還有對海洋的訊息不是那麼大
Therefore, the first image data left is very little
所以圖像資料留下來的第一個非常少
The second factory manager is not accurate
第二個廠長不太準
we're going to take a look now
我們現在就要看一下
There are some records about Jintun’s offshore activities in Chinese history
中國史上有關於金屯在近海活動的一些記載
give some examples
例舉一些材料
First of all, in Hebei near Shangguan Customs
首先就是在河北的靠近商海關
on the coast of this place
這個地方的海岸上
it is documented
它在文獻上記載
There will be a very large fish in this place
這個地方會有一種很大的魚
This is called bigger than a square
這個叫做比方子還大
called yellow croaker
叫黃魚
sometimes it cuts shallow on the shore
有時候它會割淺在海岸上
After the locals cut the meat
當地人就把肉割了之後
take it to boil oil
拿去煮熬油
This record lasted from the Ming Dynasty to the Qing Dynasty
這個記載一直到從明代到清代
There are relevant records
都有相關的記載
until the Republic of China
一直到民國時期
Here in Bohai Bay
在渤海灣這裏
Fishermen of this generation in the Bohai Sea
渤海海域這一代的漁民
still call the gold class the old yellow croaker
仍然稱金類為老黃魚
But the name of Jintun in various places
可是各個地方對於金屯的名稱
It's not the same
其實不太一樣
Hebei called yellow croaker
河北叫黃魚
But this Shandong coast
可是這個山東沿海
also known as squid
又叫它鱲魚
For example, it is said in a record at the place of the yellow line in the last year of the dynasty that
比如說明朝末年在黃線這個地方的一條記載裡面講到
He said that this fish is often ten or twenty feet long
他說這個魚常常常有一二十丈
Every time they are active on the sea, they are in groups of three or four
每次在海面上活動的時候都三五成群
and spray that wave
而且會噴那個浪
It looks like it's snowing
好像在下雪這樣子
Anyway, his record is quite realistic.
反正他的記載這個也蠻寫實
It's because Jintun has a habit
就是因為金屯類它有一種習慣
It will spray air upwards in front of the air hole
會當著氣孔會往上噴氣
The jet will cause a shower of snow that looks like
噴氣就會造成很像的雪灑下來
In it, he also specifically recorded that this kind of Jintun
裡面他還特別記載到說這種金屯類
He can even swallow a boat when his mouth opens
他嘴巴打開的時候甚至可以把一條船吞進去
So sometimes it's called swallowing a boat
所以有時候又叫吞船啦
There are relevant records until the Republic of China
一直到民國都有相關的記載
There is a man in Wei County, Shandong, who is a scholar named Chen Hengqing
有一個人在山東圍縣有一個讀書人叫陳恆慶
He mentioned in it that the place near the sea is often
他裡面就講到說近海這個地方常常會
There will be dragon soldiers on the sea
海面上會有龍兵
Jintun
他把金屯
Dragon soldiers
列隊將經過叫做龍兵
Dragon soldiers pass by
龍兵整隊而過
The leader of the gunfish
領隊的砲魚
There will be holes in the top of the fish
魚頂上會有孔
it jets
它會噴氣
The breath comes out and there is sound with sound
噴出來的氣還有聲音帶著聲音
looks like a cannon
好像砲的樣子
This is the record in Shandong
這個就是山東這方面的記載
Now let's see that this is
下面我們看就是這個就是
the way it blows
經它噴氣的樣子
But in Jiangsu this place is called
可是在江蘇這個地方稱
There is nothing special about Jintun class
金屯類沒有特別的一些
some titles
有些稱呼
But it is most often referred to as
可是它最常提到的就是
a very large fish usually called a quarter fish
通常叫季魚很大的魚
Sometimes it's funny when you read this record
有時候你看這個記載就很有趣
Just think it looks like a carp
就是把它認為它跟鯉魚很像
and it will be in
而且它會在
This one on the sea is tumbling in the air
海面上這個騰空翻滾
This is of course a very realistic record.
這個當然也是很寫實的一個記載
This place in Fujian is quite special.
福建這個地方就比較特別
that is
就是說
For example, in Fujian, let’s look at the Matsu
福建比如說我們看那個馬祖這個
This place in Lianjiang County
連江縣市這個地方
It is recorded that they often have
記載他們這個海面上常常會有
Four species of this fish related to Jintun
四種跟金屯有關的這種魚類
what's their name
他們的稱呼呢
But the first one he called the porcupine fish
可是第一個他稱呼叫海豬魚
He said that the nose will spray air
他說這個鼻子上面會噴氣
In addition, CNOOC
另外就是海油
That's the biggest possibility
那就是最大的這種可能
Refers to this relatively large type of gold
指這種比較大的那個金類
Another third type is called sea pigs
另外第三類叫海豬
But if you use this local dialect
可是如果你用這個當地的方言
How about comparing this sea pig with a sea pig?
把這個海豬跟海豬呢
Put it all together, it might actually be the same fish
拼起來其實它可能是同一種魚
That's the dolphin
那這就是豚海豚
It's actually the same as that A and that sea pig.
跟那個A那個海豬其實都是一樣的
But he recorded that it is divided into two types
可是他記載上面把它分成兩種
In addition, he also recorded a fourth species called cross fish
另外他還有記載第四種叫做跨魚
That
那
In this cross fish, it is also specifically written that
這個跨魚裡面還特別寫到說
it belongs to shark
它是屬於鯊魚類
but you get used to it
可是你從它的習慣
That is to say, we have the habit of looking at the records behind it.
就是說我們看它後面的記載的習慣
you know it's probably tiger spirit or something
你就知道它是可能是虎精或是一類的
It's closer to that
就是比較接近於就是那個
Shark-like teeth are sharp
比較像鯊魚的那種牙齒很尖銳
And it's the biting kind
而且它是用飼咬的那種
that's how it rolls
也是這樣會翻滾
Because if a shark doesn't have this habit
因為如果鯊魚的話它是不太有這種習慣
In short, basically in this place in Fujian
總之基本上在福建這個地方
The records of fine buttocks are relatively detailed
對於精臀類的記載就相對比較細緻
Of course, the classification above in traditional records is sometimes compared
當然傳統記載上面的分類有時候是比較
Not so different from our modern natural history classification
沒有那麼跟我們現代的博物學的分類已經比較不一樣
At that time it was more traditional
那當時候比較傳統
So it's not very precise, it's actually inevitable
所以不太精確這個其實很必然
Then this is what I just mentioned, it is more like the sand
那這個就是剛剛講到就是比較像那個沙類
floating gold
的這種浮金
his appearance
他的這種長相
because of the most important feature behind him
就因為他後面最重要的特徵
Just like a shark, his fins
就是跟鯊魚一樣他的鰭
he will show the tail fin
尾鰭他會露出來
and he looks like a shark
而且他看起來很像鯊魚
Now let's look at Taiwan
那現在我們要看台灣
is Taiwan
就是台灣
he continued this
他延續的這個
There are some names that are actually a bit like Southern Fujian
有一些名稱其實跟閩南有點像
He speaks in our Taiwanese Hokkien dialect
他用我們台語的閩南話來講
just hi ang
就就是嗨昂
Like this pig spiral in Kangxi
像這個康熙的這個豬螺線裡面
The record is Hayon
記載就是海翁
He is Haiyou
他就是海有
can swallow a boat
大能吞舟
on the lake water
在湖嶼水面
this color on that back
那個背部的這個顏色
It's like a bull's back
是很像牛背
The latter record is the most interesting
那後面這個記載最有趣
That is to say, as long as he appears
就是說他只要一出現的時候
the big one will appear
就會出現大的那個
Maybe there's a typhoon or something like that
可能有颱風或是什麼這類的
this storm comes out
這個風暴出來
in 1722
那1722年的時候
In fact, there was an official in the Qing Dynasty who was ordered
其實清朝有一個官員奉命的
Come to Taiwan form
來台灣形式
it's in it's this
它在它的這個
inside this record of the form
形式的這個紀錄裡面
jellyfish
記載了這種海翁魚
he said probably
他說大概
This local fisherman told him
當地的這個漁民跟他講說
About three or four thousand catties
大概有三四千斤
The small one weighs about a thousand kilograms
那小的大概有一千多斤
that sometimes called
那有時候又叫
another name
又有其他人名稱
for example
比如說
Later he mentioned this, this sea
後面他提這個這個海
sea ​​tree
海樹
In fact, in Taiwanese, it is Haidu.
其實用台語來講就是海都
That is the head looks like a pig
那就是頭很像豬
The big one weighs about a thousand catties
大的大概有一千多斤
The small one is about five or six hundred catties
小的大概五六百斤
That likes to get up on the water
那喜歡在水面上要起
Then this is very similar to the habit of that dolphin
那這個就很像那個海豚的習慣
This is the record of Taiwan
這個是台灣的記載
Actually quite a lot
其實還蠻多的
Just moments
只是類矩而已
let's see now
那現在我們看一下
This coast of Guangdong
廣東的這個沿海
Its record actually has some
它這個記載其實有一些
With Minnan and the one just mentioned
跟閩南還有剛剛講的這個
The record in the northern part of the lake is almost the same
湖見北部的這個記載差不多
You see, the first type is sea pigs
就是你看就是第一類就是海豬
that ball is the second category
那球是第二類
The third category is called Baifeng
那第三類叫拜風
thanks to the wind
拜風其實
it means big
它就是說大
Much like this sea pig but he likes to jump
很像這個海豬但是他這個喜歡跳
But I think this one might be related to Class A.
可是這個我覺得可能是跟A類呢
In fact, it was when he was observing
其實都是他在觀察的時候
What you see is his different shape
所看到他不一樣的這個形狀
In addition, there is a record in the political years
另外在從政年間有一個記載
This is of course closer to the South China Sea.
這個當然已經比較接近南海了
This, that, Zhao Qingfu, this place
這個那個趙慶福這個地方
It's in the Yangjiang area
就是在陽江那一帶
He has three types of gold
他有三種那個金屯類
The first type is called sea loach
那第一類叫海鰍
The second type is called cattle fish
第二類叫做牛魚
third call
第三叫屯
Then in terms of his category
那他這個分類上面來講
basically already relatively possible
基本上已經相對是可能
slightly better
稍微好一點
That is to say
那總之就是說
tradition for that
傳統對於那個
Especially after the Ming and Qing dynasties
特別到明朝清朝以後
As for the activities of that goldfish on the surface of the sea
對於那個金屯類在海面上的活動
And his classification has begun to be more detailed
還有他的那個分類已經開始比較細緻
Before the Ming Dynasty, there were relatively few
那在明代以前就是相對比較少
There was just a document mentioned above
那剛剛有一條文獻上面提到
It's his goldfish on the back of his fish
就是他那個金屯類的他那個魚背上
sometimes some
有時候會有一些
parasitic things
寄生的東西
That's actually Fujitora
那其實那個就是藤虎
Fujitora will parasitize in
藤虎會寄生在
Especially this sad one with some whales
特別是那個有一些鯨魚的這個悲傷
there are some records
那還有一些記載
it's not just on the sea
它不只是在海面的
And it has already swam into the inner river and the inner border
而且它是已經游到那個內河內疆裡面
There are many records
這個記載也不少
The earliest record is in AD 837
最早一條記載是在西元837年的時候
There is a big fishing ground slipping up
有一條很大的漁場溜漲
Swim from that Yellow Sea into this Huaihe River
從那個黃海游進這個懷河
later on that
後來到了那個
Many people in this place killed him
好多這個地方被老百姓把他殺了
That was until the early years of the Republic of China
那一直到民國初年
In this Haizhou area is the Lianjiang
在這個海洲一帶就是那個連江
The one near Lianyungang
那個連雲港那附近
because there are some
因為那裡面有一些
there are some rivers
有一些河
It was dug by hand
它是那個人工挖掃的
This kind of river connected with the canal
跟運河連接的這種河道
There will often be some Jintun Lie swimming in
裡面常常會有一些金屯列游進來
One of them is Guanhe
其中有一條叫灌河
But every July and August
但在每年七八月的時候
There is that Uyghur gold
都有那個維吾金
He swam inward from that estuary
那個他從那個河口一直往內游
but he is weird
但是他很奇怪
He swam to one place and went back
他游到一個地方就回去了
That place is in the Dragon King Temple
那個地方在龍王廟
So the local folks said that it was a goldfish to worship the Dragon King
所以當地民間就說那個是金魚來拜龍王
I'll go back after saying goodbye
拜完就回去了
The Yangtze River is very special
長江這個地方非常特別
Everyone knows him because of the Yangtze River
他因為長江大家知道
The Yangtze River is very wide
那個長江的河道非常的寬
The collar is also very large
索領也非常大
So this goldfish he swam in
所以他游進來的這個金屯類
sometimes very big
有時候非常的大
For example, in the Southern Tang Dynasty
比如說在那個南唐
During the Five Dynasties, when the descendants of the Southern Tang Dynasty
五代的時候南唐後祖的時候
There is a big sea ball
有一條很大的這個海球
he started from
他就從
He described it as a big body
他形容就是好像一個很大的這個體一樣
cut money there
在那邊割錢
It says that the long tree is a funeral
上面寫說長樹是葬
Near the current Jiujiang
在現在的那個九江那附近
That's the place in Jiujiang, Hukou of Boyang Lake, where the money is cut.
就是伯陽湖的湖口九江那地方就割錢在那邊
Then why can we judge that he is Jintun class?
那裡面我們為什麼可以判定他是金屯類呢
Because he was still spraying water when he was on fire
因為他火的時候他還在噴水
It's the water, it's the air
就是那個水就是噴那個氣
Spray paint from the brain
從腦那邊噴漆出來
The following is the one about Dongting Lake
下面就是那個講到洞亭湖
It is recorded in the young magenta clay potion of Dongting Lake that
洞亭湖這一條幼洋紅土劑裡面記載說
This fisherman in the area of ​​Dongting Lake
洞亭湖一帶的這個漁民
will catch this jerk
會去捕這個江臀
This is Jiang hip
這個就是江臀
It may be a different experience than the one swimming in above.
跟那個上面游進來可能是經歷不一樣
Use various schemes to catch
用各種方案去捕
looks a little cruel
看起來有點殘忍
In fact, the record of the buttocks of the Yangtze River is very early.
其實長江的江臀記載非常早
Someone once verified that
有人曾經考證過說
There is a word in goose and duck called remember
鵝鴨裡面有一個字叫做記
This should be that white butt
這個應該就是那個白季臀
that of course might be a bit far fetched
那當然可能有點牽強
However, we can see from the records in the literature that
不過我們從那個文獻上記載可以看出來
That is, at least in the Ming Dynasty
就是至少在明代的時候
like in 1564
像1564年的時候
In fact, in this Jiangnan area
其實在這個江南這一帶
There is such a record of Bai Jiyu
就有那個白季臀的這種記載
he is white
他是白色的
later cut money
後來割錢
Of course this record is very special
那當然這條記載非常特別
That is to say, at that time, there were many sea areas heading towards this area.
就是說那時候就是有很多這個海域往這個
This Xinyangjiang this
這個新陽江這個
Jiangai
江內
It's very loud, like a cow is braying
聲音非常大 好像牛在叫
More than 1,000 people went to see
去看的人有1000多人
But then there are some people who don't know what to do
但是後來就是有一些不知道亂遊
swim into a small river port
遊到一個小河港裡面
He was later found alive
後來被發現他還活著
Just cut money on the river beach
就割錢在河灘上
was finally killed
最後被打死
This is Baijitun
這個是白季屯
Of course Baijitun on the Yangtze River
當然長江的白季屯
There is very little stock now
現在存流已經非常少
Become a rare unarmed
變成稀有的不武類
have been included in their
已經被列入他們
China's protected animals
中國保護的動物
animal protection
之類的保護動物
In addition, we have to look at
另外就是我們要看
Like some aspects of this record
像有一些方面這個記載
Also this record is what the front hall said
也是這條記載是前堂講的
There are other related records
還有其他的都有相關的記載
This is another picture of Baijitun
這個是白季屯的另外一個圖
In fact, there are related records in Fujian
在福建地區其實有相關的記載
We won't talk about the relationship of time
時間的關係我們就不多講
This place in Jeonju is where we hold
全州這個地方就是我們舉行的
This example is fine
這個例子就好
It's at the Ma Xiang Hall in Jeonju
就是在全州府的馬項廳
There was a record in this place that
這個地方曾經就有記載到說
It comes from this Tong'an County
它從這個同安縣的這個
A small river in the west is called Xixi
西邊的一條小河叫西西
20 miles up
往上有了20幾里
Now we're talking about that
下面我們談的是那個
about that Chinese history
有關於那個中國歷史上
This kind of space-time distribution of the money cutting in this gold mine
這個金屯割錢的這種時空分布
I've read about this in total
我總共大概查閱了這個
in the relevant information
相關的資料中
There are a total of 176 records related to this
總共有176起的這個相關的記錄
among them
其中呢
If we divide it according to the four major regions of China
如果我們按這個中國四大海域來分的話
Most of them are in the East China Sea
最多的是東海海域
A total of 112 times
總共有112次
More than the sum of the other three sea areas
超過那個其他三個海域的這個總和
Why is there more in the East China Sea?
東海為什麼會比較多呢
maybe the first place is this place
可能第一個就是這個地方
This colorful shore line is relatively long
這個彩岸線比較長
The second is that there are two relatively large rivers flowing into the East China Sea.
第二個就是這個東海有兩條比較大的河會入
One is the Yangtze River and the other is the former Yangtze River
一個是長江 另外一個是前長江
Their estuaries are very large
他們的江口都非常的大
near here because there are many lakes with living things and related fish
在這附近因為有很多湖有生物跟相關的魚類
So Jintun will hunt here
所以金屯會在這邊捕食
may in some cases
可能在某一些情況下
He just cut money at the mouth of the Yangtze River and before the mouth of the Yangtze River
他就割錢在長江口跟前長江口
This is the classification of the approximate number of times
這個是大概的次數的分類
let's take a look
我們要看一下
It's probably the season for him to cut money
大概是他割錢的季節
About what months
大概是在哪幾個月
First, there is an interesting record
首先有一條比較有趣的記載
It was in the Jin Dynasty that there was a book called Gu Jinzhu
就是在晉朝的時候有一個書叫古金柱
he mentioned goldfish
他提到說金魚
Because the ancients regarded this gold as a fish
因為古代人把這個金當作魚
So I held on to them
所以他們當時我就撐住
In fact, it should not educate
實際上它照理講不應該教育
Where is the goldfish hiding in May and June?
那金魚呢藏在這個五六月的時候
give birth on the shore
在岸邊呢就生小孩
Then in July and August, it will guide this
那七八月的時候就會那個引導這個
It's this paper towel and it returns to the sea
它的這個紙巾呢就回歸到大海
There will be some walruses on one side and the other will be different
那一邊有一邊會有一些海象就會不一樣
Well, there are other records that say
那但是另外有記載就講到說
Like the sunny side of this generation in Shandong
像山東這一代的陽面
Its silkworm season is not in May and June
它蠶子的季節不是在五六月
it is march in spring
它是在春天的三月
Then he said that gave birth to this little fish?
那他說那個生出來這個小魚呢
eyes are not open yet
眼睛都還沒開
But it's bigger than three houses
可是它已經比三間房子都還大
That's probably why this place is so miserable
那可能就是這個地方這個慘的
Maybe it's a false alarm or something.
可能就是虛驚之類的
bigger
要大一點
What's more interesting is that
比較有趣的是那個
In the meaning of Liao disaster
遼災之意裡面
Record Shandong Binghai people
記載山東冰海人
he has a habit
他有一種習慣
That is to say, before and after the Ching Ming Festival
就是說他在清明節的前後
will see the heavy rain in this sea
會看到這個海中的大雨
Take his little fish to the sea
帶著他的小魚往海面上走
go around on land
陸地上來繞
The locals describe it as
當地人就形容說
That is to ask that to bring this son and daughter here
那個是拜那個帶著這個兒女來這邊
That one is called Baimu
那個那個叫做拜穆
Of course this is my own imagination
當然這個是自己人的想像
human imagination
人類的想像
Other records are of course different.
那其他記載當然各自有不同
Maybe the latitude of each sea area
可能各個海域它的那個緯度
It's different from the temperature of the sea water
跟那個海水的溫度不一樣
So they are miserable
所以他們慘暖
It's not the season of misfortune
不是慘殖的季節不一樣
Like this area in southwestern Guangdong
像這個廣東西南這一帶的
Records on this sea
這個海面上的記載
That is to say they were in February
就是說他們是在2月的時候
From this record
那從這個記載看來
We don't care how many pages he breeds here
我們不管就是他幾頁在這邊殖子
It can be seen that in this coastal place
可見就是說在這個沿海地方
in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
在明清的時候
This place, this ocean, this environment are very good
這個地方的這個海洋的這個環境都非常好
So at that time the Jintun class
所以那個時候的這個金屯類
still very much distributed
還是分佈得非常多
Then I have done statistics on that record
那我曾經做過統計對於那個有記載
This incident in that shallow month
那個隔淺月份的這個事件
Use this record for statistics
用這個記載來做統計
Among them, there are about 30 cases in spring.
那其中呢大概就春天大概有三十起
Because there are some documents he only records the year
因為有一些有些文獻他只記年
I won't remember the month and season
不會記那個月份季節
Some are seasons and some are years
有些是記季節有些是記年份而已
So carefully remember the month
那所以仔細記到月份的呢
Basically, this figure is relatively speaking
基本上統計的這個數字相對來講
not so much
就不是那麼多
But now we can see
不過我們現在可以看出來
That is to say, spring is the most
就是說春天是最多的
the rest is next in autumn
其餘接下來是秋天
But the numbers in summer and autumn are not much different.
那但是夏天跟秋天的數字也沒差多少
Generally speaking, spring 30
總體來講春天30
Most are spring 30
最多的是春天30
least winter 21
最少的冬天21
In fact, there is not much difference in numbers.
其實數字上也沒有差多少
So I can't see if they have a specific
所以也看不出他們是不是有特定的
That is to say, in a certain season can
就是說在某個季節能夠
They are easier to cut money
他們比較會容易割錢
so now we're going to look at
那現在我們要看一下
This is the place where the money was cut
就是那個割錢的這個地點
Let's look at this picture
下面我們看這張圖
This picture is actually very obvious that it can be seen
這張圖其實很明顯就是可以看出來
It's the place where he cut money
就是那個他割錢的一些地方
The first one is in the Bohai Bay
第一個就是在那個渤海灣
It's just what we said
就是剛剛我們曾經講過說
People in Hebei call it Huangyu
河北人稱黃雨那個地方
It's near the Shanghai Customs
就靠近上海關那個地方
On this north side of Bohai Bay
在那個渤海灣的這個北面
what about this place
這個地方呢
There are relatively many records of cutting money
割錢的記載相對也比較多
The second is Laizhou Bay
第二個就是萊州灣
from the two men
從那個兩漢開始
Laizhou Bay has a lot of records
萊州灣這個地方記載就非常多了
That is to say, we just talked about Beihai County
就是說剛剛我們講到北海郡
Laiju County
萊州郡
This place is early
這個地方都是比較早就
In the Ming and Qing Dynasties, there were relatively more places in this place
暗地到明清時期這個地方也是相對多一點
The third place is Haizhou Bay in the north of Intermodal Port
第三個地方就是海周灣在聯運港的北面
This place borders Shandong and Jiangsu
跟山東跟江蘇交界這個地方
It is also a place with a relatively large curvature.
也是一個彎的弧度相對大的地方也有一點
The vicinity of the intermodal port is because it was the outlet of the Yellow River in the Ming and Qing Dynasties
聯運港附近因為是明清時期的黃河的出海口
Because the Yellow River once sucked the Huaihe River
因為黃河曾經有一段時間吸奪了淮河
go to sea from here
從這邊出海
So the area around the intermodal port was also stranded. There are more records.
所以聯運港那一帶也擱淺了這個記載比較多一點
The Yangtze Estuary is also a place with many records.
長江口也是一個記載比較多的地方
This is the second most
這是第二多的
Qiantang Bay is the place with the largest number of strandings in the entire record
前唐灣是整個記載擱淺數字最多的地方
And we now record from the literature that it is the largest number of collective strandings
而且我們現在從文獻上記載就是集體擱淺數量最大的
also appeared in former don wan
也出現在前唐灣
this place is special
這地方很特別
is the place to bend the mouth
就是地方彎了嘴巴
The tidal action is sometimes relatively large
那潮汐作用有時候相對也很大
so everyone knows
所以大家知道就是
The Haining tide watcher appeared just to the north of the former guard
那個海寧關潮就出現在那個前黨官的北邊
when his tide is in a certain season
那個他的潮汐在某一個季節的時候
especially during the mid-autumn festival
特別是這樣中秋的時候
His tide is very high
他那個潮汐特別的高
This is famous all over the world
這個是全世界有名的
That may be because of the Guanyin of the tide
那可能因為潮汐的觀音
Will suck that with some of this fine ass this way
會把那個有一些這個精臀類往這邊吸
So what about his Ji Zai?
所以他的季仔呢
relatively more
相對也比較多
The other number that collectively stranded
另外那個集體擱淺的數字
we'll give it later
待會我們舉一下
next is
接下來就是
wednesday island generation
周三島一代
Because his island is also distributed more
因為他那個島嶼分布也比較多
And it is the largest fishing ground in China
而且是中國最大的漁場
All kinds of fish are here
各種魚類在這邊
there are a lot of resources
那個資源非常多
There are many fish resources
魚類資源非常多
Maybe Jintun is here to supplement the food.
那可能金屯在這邊補食的這個
The situation is also more obvious
情況也比較明顯
that sometimes in some
那有時候在一些
They ran aground by accident
意外狀況下他們就擱淺了
this is that number
這個是那個數字
Everyone can take a look
大家可以看一下
There are a total of 45 incidents in Qiantangwan and 35 incidents in the mouth of the Yangtze River. These are the two largest and most
前唐灣總共有45起,長江口35起,這是兩個最大的最多的
The reason for the song spring, the traditional records about the song spring, why is there a song spring? There are very few records of this
歌泉的原因,傳統的記載對於歌泉,為什麼會歌泉?這個記載非常少
The first record tells that the ocean will have this kind of inertia every autumn.
第一條記載講說每年的秋天的時候海洋就會有這種慣性
It will start to be called a habit that will push some things on the sea surface to the land
就會開始要叫做有一種習慣就會把海面上有些東西往陸地上推
The local people recorded that these are the three sayings about the people nearby
當地人就記載,這是三有關附近的人的說法
He said it would push something up
他說就會把有些東西往上推
push push push some damn fish inland
推推推就會把一些該死的魚往內陸上推
Pushing up this phenomenon is called Xihai
推上去這種現象叫做習海
So in the process some big fish will also
所以在這個過程當中有一些大的魚也會
just up there
就各前在上面那邊
The Western missionary at the end of the Qing Dynasty once mentioned that
那清朝末年那個西洋的傳教士曾經提到說
Why are there so many front halls?
那個前堂江口為什麼是比較多呢
They also observed that more
他們也觀察到說是比較多
Then what he said was
那他的說法就是說
Because that's a funnel shaped bay
因為那個這是一個漏斗型的這個海灣
That tide is so big
那個潮汐特別的大
So he becomes that whale's trap
所以他就變成那個鯨魚的陷阱
Will suck this goldfish over and die here
會把這個金屯類吸過去就會死在這裡
So this is a more scientific statement
所以這個是那個比較科學的一個說法
But even if the current scientific research is not clear
但是就是說現在科學的研究也搞不清楚
Why is there Jintun
說為什麼會有金屯
Why did Jintun cut the money and go there
金屯為什麼會割錢會往那個
In fact, there are many sayings now, and there is no specific one.
其實現在說法非常多沒有特定的一個
It is a conclusion that can fully explain
就是能夠完全解釋的一個定論
Next we'll look at the scale
接下來我們要看那個規模
So we're going to look at the scale
所以我們要看這個規模
First, let's take a look at a record in Taiwan.
首先我們先看一下台灣的一個記載
This record is in the ninth year of the dragon
這條記載就是在前龍九年的時候
Nasutu, the civil governor, once reported that
民政總督納蘇土曾經做報說
That last year was December 18 of the previous year
那個去年就是前一年的12月18日
Baishatun in Hokuriku, Taiwan
在台灣北陸白沙屯
Baishatun is in the area of ​​the current night
白沙屯在現在的那個通宵那一帶
that all night with that
那通宵那一帶有那個
22 very large fish
很大的魚22條
That mow dives into that sea
那割潛在那個海面上
What about the head he said?
那他說那個頭呢
The mouth of the big tent fish is four feet wide
大帳魚口闊四尺
That belly is two tent tail big heptapod
那個肚子寬二帳尾大七尺魚
Then his description said that the tail is very similar to the tail of a shrimp
那他的描述說這個尾巴很像蝦子的尾巴
But it's fish body, etc. There are some related records
但是是魚身等等等等有一些相關的記載
It's not dead yet, it's screaming like a cow, that cow is screaming
那還沒死那聲音叫得像牛那個牛在叫一樣
At that time, it was not yet fully
那當時候就是還沒有完全
It's just that the tide may not have fully receded yet.
就是潮汐可能還沒完全退
It's the shallow tide
就是水潮割淺
don't know what it's called
不知道那是叫什麼
more interesting it has a follow up
比較有趣它有一個後續的
It was when this mantra was reported to the former Dragon Emperor
就是這個咒報報到前龍皇帝那邊的時候
The former Dragon Emperor later issued an order
前龍皇帝後來下了一個命令
Just pointed down and said show me that fish painting
就下指說把那個魚畫給我看
Later, Nasu land was called Taiwan government.
後來納蘇土就叫台灣府
After painting the soil
把這個土就畫了之後
Dust to the former Dragon Emperor
塵上給前龍皇帝
But now we are on the Forbidden City archives
但是現在我們在故宮檔案上面
It's a pity I can't find this soil
找不到這張土比較可惜
In addition, of course, the above is the record of the mantra
另外當然上面是那個咒數的記載
Below we are the records of Taiwan's government system
下面我們是台灣府制的記載
That description isn't much different either.
那描述也也差不了多少
In addition, comrades were in Yilan in 1872
另外就是在同志1872年的時候在宜蘭
This seaport in Gemaran
格馬蘭的這個海口
It is now the estuary of Lanyang Creek
就是現在的蘭陽溪的河口
There are 7 heavy rains also cut shallow in that place
有7條大雨也是割淺在那個地方
At the same time, if you intend to entrust it to Danshui, you will also cut shallow
那同一個時間有意委在淡水這個地方也割淺
that's pretty big
那都蠻大了
Then in 1881
那另外在1881年的時候
This deep storm also reported that in the Hengjiang area
這個深暴也報導那個在那個恆江這一帶
Where is this Hengjiang?
這個恆江在哪裡呢
It's probably a little bit inside the Qiantang River
大概就是在那個前堂江的稍微靠裡面
There are a lot of this fish dove dive
有很多這個魚鴿潛
inexplicable
莫名其數
Its inexplicable name is very large
它那個莫名叫數量非常的大
even that boat iron lock
連那個船 鐵鎖
It seems that the iron locks all the ones near the Hengjiang River
好像鐵鎖把那個恆江這個附近的那個都那個
Stopped, the boat can't pass
攔住了 船都過不了
That record is the one I found with the largest number
那一條記載是那個我找到數量最大的
Qiantangjiang
就是剛剛講前堂江
This is the pigeon dive of a certain countryman
這個是那個某鄉親鴿潛的
That this one is in a foreign country
那個這個是在外國的
are dead
都已經死了
The records of Jintun in Gequan in the traditional literature
那傳統文獻上對於隔泉的金屯的記載
Some records are very clear and some are very exaggerated
有些記載的非常清楚 有些非常誇張
The number is somewhat, for example, a few examples
數量有些譬如說幾個例子
There is a record that once recorded that it was more than a hundred feet
有記載曾經記載說那個超過百丈
Of course we will think this is an exaggeration
那當然我們會覺得這個當然是誇大
Anyway, it's an adjective, so we have to take it seriously.
反正是形容詞 我們就不得不要當真
However, there are some records that the recorded size is very fine
不過有一些記載到是記載的尺寸非常精細
Most of the records can be seen
大部分的記載可以看出來
That is, if we look at the three grids in front
就是我們如果看前面的三格
That is, the largest number is about six feet to ten feet.
就是數量最多的大概是到六丈到十丈了
previous most
以前的最多
But there is a second one that is tens of feet long
但是還有第二個就是十數丈的
This one is at the back where there are nineteen records
這個就在後面那個地方就是有十九條記載
Probably we can see from this record
大概我們可以從這個記載來看
It's the approximate number
就是大概隔淺的這個數字
Probably from this size to that size
大概就從這個大小的那個尺寸
Most of them are under 20 accounts
大概是都是在20帳以下比較多
That's probably the place where the yellow color is on top of me now.
那大概我現在上面黃色那個地方
Said about 20 tents about 60 meters
說大概20帳大概約60公尺
In fact, this is to use the official account to go to that
其實這個是用官方的官帳去去那個
But what we need to know is that the Chinese folk
可是就是我們要知道就是中國的民間
That is to say, every place they have will have their own one called Xiaozhang
就是說他們每個地方都會有他們自己的那個叫做小帳
That is, they are like our golden food in private
那個就是他們私底下就像我們那個金糧
Gold grain is not the same
金糧也不一樣
The public gold is different from the general Taiwan gold
那個公金跟那個一般的台金也不一樣
that would be relatively small
那會相對小
So that is to say, if we convert it into the relatively small folk tent
所以也就是說如果我們把它換算成那個民間的這種比較小的這個華帳的話
It may be relatively smaller
那相對來講可能它會更小
But we, I really can't find out what the number of its luxury tents is in each place, and I don't remember much.
可是我們我實在找不到說每個地方到底是它的華帳大概是多少這個數字也記得不多
Probably strictly speaking, if we divide it by two-thirds or half
大概嚴格來講大概如果我們再給它除以三分之二的話或是一半的話
The size of this is about four or five
這個之大大概是這大四五
It's about 40 to 50 meters at most, and it's already very big.
最多大概是四五十公尺大概已經很大
In fact, pigeons dive these big fish in the sea
其實鴿潛在海面上的這些大的魚
It's what it's called. It's different in different places.
就叫什麼其實各個地方不同的
all we've just said
全部剛剛我們已經講過了
The picture we see below is also a picture of the West
下面我們看的這個也是西方的一張圖
also a kind of engraving
也是一種版畫
People's paintings are relatively normal
人家畫的就是比較正常
And this pair is interesting
而且這張對有趣
That is, he recorded the scene and still has the size of an elephant
就是他把場景錄還有大象的尺寸
Compared with the military instrument of the pigeon dive
跟鴿潛的軍儀來做對比
and horses and people
還有馬 還有人
In fact, it is impossible to exaggerate to say more than 60 meters
其實不可能誇張到說六十公尺以上
That size is actually very, very scary
那樣的尺寸其實已經非常非常可怕
probably unlikely
大概不太可能
The following is an analysis of some cases of death
下面看的就是一些死亡的個案的分析
Some records will be recorded in a special way
有一些記載會記載得比較特別
that is why he died
就是說他為什麼會死
For example, there is a record that said he
譬如說有一條記載講到說他
There was a man whose father was an official in Haicheng County, Zhangzhou Prefecture
有一個人在他父親在張州府海城縣這個地方當官
One day when he was an officer, he saw two big fish peeling beans on the sea
當官的時候有一天他看到有兩條大魚在海面上打剝豆
Three days after the peeling, a fish got stuck on the reef in the sea
那剝完之後三天以後有一條魚就卡在那個海面的礁石
Can't move on the reef next to the Han
這個漢邊的礁石上動彈不得
Probably one of them has already left
大概有一條已經就離開了
Then this money cutting died on this reef
那這一條割錢在這個礁石上後來就死了
We know that even the gold species will actually supplement their own kind.
我們知道就是金類他們其實也會補食自己同類的
For example, Fu Jin is the most familiar to everyone.
比如說那個福金就是大家最耳熟能想的
So he asked Fujin to attack those such as blue gold or virtual gold
所以他向福金會去攻擊那個比如說藍金或者虛金類
Then this record may be relatively speaking
那這一條記載可能相對來講有可能是
A record of Fu Jin going to attack other gold classes
福金去攻擊其他的金類的一條記載
This is Fukin
這是福金
Bite other coppers
在咬其他的銅類
Also, it will be recorded that
還有就是會記載到說
It is especially easy to cut money in the gold mine during the storm
在暴風雨的時候特別容易有一些金屯內割錢
This was about seven or eight years ago
這個是在大概七八年前
In this place in Haiyan County, Northern Subei
在蘇北海岩縣這個地方
There is a photo of that township cutting money
有那個某鄉金割錢的一個照片
many people run
很多人跑去
It is even recorded that
甚至有人還有記載講到
It is said that some people cut the meat and cooked it
說後來有人還割了肉回去煮
Another record is that the tide suddenly rose
另外一個記載就是海潮突然大漲
In particular, the typhoon washes up the sea water in the nearby sea area.
特別是颱風把附近海域的海水往上沖
Traditionally, this kind of sea area will be called
傳統都會叫這種海域
would push some really big fish up the shore
就會把一些很大的魚往海岸上推擠
After the push they cut the money
推擠之後他們就割錢
This record is relatively more
這個記載也相對比較多一點
This is a photo from France
這個是法國的一條照片
After the storm, this virtual crystal was left in that place
暴風雨過後,這條虛晶就擱減在那個地方
What's more special is that there are two records related to the earthquake
比較特別就是有兩條記載講到跟地震有關
But those earthquakes are actually far behind in time.
但是那些地震其實時間差有些差得比較遠
We're not entirely sure if it's just an earthquake under the sea.
我們就也不能完全確定是不是就是海底有地震
Sometimes there are records of some heavy rain
有時候會有一些記載講到有一些大雨
It dies and is slaughtered on the sea
它死就在海面上宰成宰糊的
This can be seen in the modern photos I collected
這個在我所搜集到的這個現代的照片當中可以看得到
The most frequently documented is why they cut money
最常出現的記載就是為什麼他們會割錢
I mean, they go after fishing boats or merchant ships.
就講到就是說他們追漁船或是商船
Keep chasing and chasing, the boat will sail in
一直追一直追,船就開進
That river port, they still continued to chase
那個河港 結果他們還是繼續追
As a result, the river channel inside is relatively shallow.
結果追到裡面這個河道就相對比較淺
he cut shallow
他就割淺了
There are many records of this kind in the Qing Dynasty
這種記載在清代很多
And this place in the south of the Yangtze River is very special
而且江南的這個地方特別的多
Like this place is the home of Xinfu in the north of Zhejiang, Pingwu County
像這個地方是浙江北部的家新府 平無縣
scam this place
詐浮這個地方
Finally we're going to do a tidy up
最後我們要去做一個整理
there is a cultural explanation for that cut
就是有關於那個割淺的一個文化性的解釋
In fact, when the Chinese explain this about the fact that the military settlements are shallow
其實中國人在解釋這個有關於軍屯割淺的時候
Sometimes it's you speaking from your current perspective
有時候是你現在用現在的角度來講
is relatively unlearnable
是比較不可學的
He used a kind of yin and yang or Mingxin.
他用一種陰陽啦或是明信的一種說法
For example, after the Song Dynasty, this military settlement began to appear.
比如說在宋代以後就開始出現這個軍屯割淺
It's actually the dragon king.
其實就是那個龍王了
Throw some of that misbehaving or guilty fish into the army
把一些那不乖或是有罪的這個魚衝軍
where to rush to land
衝到哪裡 衝到陸地上
so he will be
所以他就會被
push inland
往內陸上推
This earliest record is the same as what was just mentioned
這個最早的記載就是跟剛剛講的
It started to appear in the heavy rain in Jiujiang before Li Hou's ancestral song
在李厚祖歌前在九江的大雨裡面就開始出現了
Of course, similar records are also mentioned in Ouyang Xiu's poems later.
後面當然在歐陽修的詩裡面也提到類似的記載
Until the Qing Dynasty, there was still the same saying
一直到清朝的時候還是有同樣的說法
That is to say, Jin Tun Geqian is because of his guilt
就是說金屯歌前都是因為他有罪
before exile after guilty conviction
在有罪定罪之後要充軍之前
Kairyumaru or Kami will take his eyes off
海龍丸或是神明就會把他的眼睛摘掉
As a result, he lost his way
結果他就迷航了
This was also said in Taiwan at the end of the Qing Dynasty
這個到清朝末年台灣也有這樣的說法
In addition, there is another special
另外還有一個比較特別的就是說
Sometimes before the song, it is because he is pressed by a big magic shrimp
有時候歌前是因為他被很大的神蝦壓著
Of course, this big shrimp is actually linked to what we just talked about.
當然這個很大的神蝦其實我們連結剛剛所講的
The one that was confiscated by Kairyu Maru
被海龍丸充軍的這個
Of course, this magical shrimp may actually be pressing the big fish to push it onto the land.
當然這個神蝦其實可能也就是壓著大魚往陸地上來推
So there will be some records like this
所以就會有些這樣的記載
But sometimes if we interpret the common people like this
但是有時候我們如果把老百姓這樣的解釋
Probably the result of his visual misreading
可能是他視覺上的誤讀的結果
because of some big false alarms
因為有一些大的虛驚
Especially when he rolls on the sea
他在海面上翻滾的時候特別是巨刺經
when his two fins rolled over the sea
他兩個鰭在海面上翻滾的時候
It's like two big boils of shrimp
就很像蝦子的兩個大熬
So let's take a look, very much like
所以我們看一下 非常的像
So if you look from far away on the coast
所以如果遠遠在很遠的海岸上看的時候
I thought it was just a shrimp
就以為這隻是神蝦
At the same time, when he was active with him
同時他跟他一起活動的時候
there will be other Jintun species next to it
就會旁邊會有其他的金屯類
Maybe soon there will be Jintun class to cut the money
可能後來不久就有金屯類就割錢了
They think this is the fish that God Shrimp was charged with
他們認為這就是神蝦被沖軍的魚
Interestingly, a saying that appeared later is called Runyu
有趣的是後來出現的一個說法叫做潤魚
I mean they observe I don't know if it's true
就是說他們觀察我不知道是不是真的
It means that generations began to observe that
就是說明代人開始觀察到說
That Jintun Geqian at this time
那個金屯戈淺的這個時間
often occurs during the lunar year
常常發生在潤年的時候
Especially the generation in the north of the Yangtze River estuary in northern Jiangsu
特別是像在蘇北長江口的北邊這一代
There are many records about this kind of legend.
記載有關於這種傳說特別的多
So it is the so-called run fish legend
所以就是所謂的潤魚傳說
It will be there in the year of Meifeng Runnian
都是美鳳潤年的時候就會有
That Jintun was pushed ashore
那個金屯被推上岸
After the Qing Dynasty, it became more detailed
到了清朝之後就講得更細了
say that every year
說那個每年的潤年
The fish that is pushed on will be very compatible with the current year's effect
被推上的魚跟當年的生效就會很相配
and looks alike
而且長得很像
For example, if it is the year of the child, it looks like a mouse
那比如說那個如果是子年的話就像老鼠
In that ugly year, his head will be like a bull
那丑年他那個頭就會像牛
Well now we'll see later
那現在我們待會我們看一下
Then this saying goes all the way to the Republic of China
那這個說法一直到民國
In the early years, there was a famous fortune teller
初年的時候還有這個算命的一個很有名的人
This occultist is called Father Yuan
這個秘密學家叫元父
He's still in that secret book of his
他還在他的那個秘密書裡面
also said that in 1909 when he
還講到說他在1909年的時候
He and his friends are in Dongtai County
他跟他的朋友在東台縣
Dongtai County is also the north bank of the Yangtze River
東台縣也是長江北 北岸
This place mentioned that there is such a phenomenon
這個地方講到說有這樣的一個現象
Then he started to push according to that over there.
那他就開始在那邊根據那個去推了
Speak as if there is something wrong with Sa
講得好像薩有其事
in fact it is
實際上根本就是
Now we'll look ridiculous
現在我們看起來就會覺得蠻可笑的
Sometimes it will be more detailed
那有時候就會記載更為的細緻
It was during the Runnian period
就是在潤年的時候
he these and that were pushed into the rain
他這些那個被推上了雨
This typhoon is often accompanied by water
也常常會伴水的這個颱風
So this is understandable as we just said
所以這個也可以理解剛剛我們講到
That's when the typhoon
就是颱風的時候那個
There will be a lot of that big rain appearing on the sea
會有很多那個大的雨出現在海面上
That's when I talked about the typhoon just now
那也有剛剛有講到說那個颱風的時候
Later there will be that
過後就會有出現那個
Of course, this is a result of two interconnected
當然這個是兩個互相連結的一個結果
Then let's take a look at this phase-by-line phase-by-line phase-by-line
那我們看一下這個相逐搞線相逐搞線
This is near the mouth of the Yangtze River
這個都是在長江口附近
It's the Legend of Runyu compared to that
就是潤魚傳說比較那個
After the Qing Dynasty
到清朝後起來
Being demoted by the Sea Dragon King combined with the legend of Runyu
被海龍王貶了跟潤魚傳說結合在一起
Of course it is more detailed
講的當然更為細緻
Let's see what this one looks like now
我們現在看一下這張像什麼
If it works
如果看生效的話
is it a bit like a snake
是不是有點像蛇
so they may be on the sea
所以他們可能在海面上
Because of the angle, the head of the gold class is different
因為角度的關係所看到的金類的頭不一樣
so they start talking nonsense
所以他們就會開始就胡說八道一通
In short, the legend of running fish is a process of accumulation
總之來講潤魚傳說是一種沉沉累積的過程
The last part we're going to talk about is
最後我們要談的一個部分就是
This batch was ancient
這一批被古代
Because in ancient times, when talking about cutting money in Jintun
因為古代在講金屯割錢的時候
often use a word
常常會用一個詞
Just treat them as dragon sea dragons
就是把他們視為龍海龍
or Dragon King Dragon
或是龍王 龍
So we're going to see after Dragon's Dive
所以我們要看龍困潛灘之後
what's the end
到底是什麼下場
The first record is the only one I found
第一條這條記載是我唯一找到
There is a record of release
就是有放生的記載
This record has appeared in the Guang Department for three years
這條記載已經出現在光系三年了
In the place of Heavy Army Island
在重兵島這個地方
There is a language about seven or eight feet long before the song
就是有一條大概七八丈的語言歌前
but it's a special place
可是它很特別的地方
Seven or eight feet is actually not too big
七八丈其實不是太大
But it found something on it
可是它在上面發現了一個東西
this one has a silver medal
這個有一條銀牌
The silver medal reads "Kangxi Seven Years Released"
銀牌上面寫著康熙七年釋放
That is to say, the phrase
也就是說這一條語
In fact, in the seventh year of Kangxi
其實在康熙七年的時候
once cut shallow after shallow cut
曾經割淺 割淺之後
pushed it back to the surface
被人把它推回海面上
It's still on the fish well in the middle
中間還在它的那個魚井上
hanging a silver medal
掛了一個銀牌
but i feel
可是我就覺得
How to hang the silver medal
那銀牌怎麼掛
how is he hanging on the neck of this fish
他怎麼掛在這個魚的頸部
Will it fall? It's unlikely.
會不會掉不太可能
that this
那這個
I think it might be a bit fictitious
我是覺得可能有點虛構
But no matter that he mentioned this matter
但是不管就是說他提到這個事情
That is to say, the Chinese used to be
也就是說中國人曾經就是
have put this
有把這個
The goldfish rescued
解救的這個金屯類
push him back to sea such a record
把他又推回海上這樣的記載
In fact, let's see some
其實下面我們看就是有一些
Then we were going to talk about the record just now
那剛剛我們要講出那一條記載
When Jintun was pushed back to sea, he had resisted Qi for seven years
金屯被推回海上的時候是抗氣七年
That connects to that later resisting Qi for seven years
那連結到那個後來抗氣七年
These 100 years
這100多年
Is that so?
那可是是不是有這樣
Jintun with such a long life
壽命這麼長的金屯
Actually there are
其實是有的
It's the referendum
就是那個公投金
The referendum gold once recorded that he lived two hundred years
公投金曾經有記錄他活了兩百年
so but we don't know
那所以但是我們不知道就是
Was that referendum money just now?
剛剛那個是不是公投金
good
好
In fact, what I just said is a lot of this
那其實我剛剛講過就是很多這個
The pigeon dog incident is often used to fall into the cage
那個鴿犬事件常常都用墮籠
that from the cage or something
那個從墮籠啊或是什麼
It's just that they don't know why this thing is here
就是他們不知道這個東西到底為什麼會出現在這裡
So it is often said that they all thought they fell from the sky
所以常常就會說他們都以為他們是從天上掉下來的
Therefore, many records mentioned above mean that
所以很多記載上面講到就是說
This cage fell from the sky
這個這個籠是從天上掉下來
after falling in that
掉下來之後在那個
Then there are some records that say there are some officials
那有一些還記載到說有一些官員呢
That one even splashed water on him
那個還用水去潑他
Tell the common people to keep pouring water on him
就叫老百姓要一直給他潑水
Because he may be in pain over there
因為他可能很痛苦在那邊啊
call over there
在那邊叫
because he's about to splash
因為他要潑水了
So ask the common people to pour water on him
所以叫老百姓給他潑水
But splashing water is useless
但潑水也沒用
Because later he only wanted him
因為後來他只要他
If he does not return to the law, he must die
不回到法上他必定要死
died three days later
三天之後就死了
The meaning of Liao disaster really needs to be recorded
那遼災之意裡面真的要記載
What about the local county magistrate?
還講到說當地的縣令呢
I used this straw tin for 80 yuan
用了80塊的這個草錫呢
cover this dragon
蓋在這個這條龍的身上
In addition is
另外是
Still worshiping him there
還在那邊祭拜他
then you can see that is to say
那你就可見就是說
It's impossible for a so-called dragon to fall from the sky
不可能有一條所謂的什麼龍從天上掉下來
He must have somehow been washed into the river
他一定是不知道怎麼情況下被沖到河道裡面
or the one that fell on the beach
或是那個掉在沙灘上
Then finally we're going to start talking about this sacrifice.
那最後我們要開始講這個祭祀
It is the one with the most sacrifices
是祭仔最多的
The most sacrificed child is that he was cut off
祭仔最多的就是他被割了
meat cut to death
肉被割到死
This sacrificial boy is more cruel
這個祭仔就比較殘忍
Those songs are very detailed
那有些歌祭仔的非常的細
Then this sacrificial boy is a sacrificial ceremony in the early years of the Southern Song Dynasty
那這條祭仔是那個南宋初年的一條祭祀
Sacrifice is also very meticulous
祭祀也非常細緻
It also talks about cutting this off
裡面還講到說這割下來這個
How much does Jin's meat sell for?
金的這個肉賣多少錢
It sells for more than 200 yuan per catty
每斤賣200多錢
It took 10 days to cut it
那割了10天才割完
There are many related sacrifices, so we won't go into details
相關的祭仔很多我們就不細講
Here is an example
那這邊舉了一個例子
Some people were poisoned to death after eating this golden meat
就是有些人吃到這個金肉後來中毒死掉
maybe that one is corrupted
可能那個已經腐敗了
is that he is dead
就是他已經死了
And corruption results in children eating
而且腐敗 結果吃了就孩子
Then some are sick and some are dead
然後有些是生病 有些是死了
We also have photos and we can see that Jintunei is dead.
我們也有照片看到就是金屯內他死了
In fact, he has already started to rot, the skin is already there
其實他都已經開始腐爛了 皮都已經那個了
And the most common one
還有就是最常那個
A lot of people cut it off and didn't eat it
他很多人割了之後不是拿去吃
mostly boiled oil
大部分都是熬油
The record of boiling oil has been around since a long time ago.
熬油的記載是從很早就有了
There are many examples, so we won't go into details
這個例子很多我們就不細講
This is Japan, they do not have a business. There is a picture in it
這個是日本他們不經業裡面有一張圖
After cutting the upper part of the body
就是把身體上部位進行切割之後
A picture of them starting to boil oil
他們就開始在熬油的一張圖
sometimes there are some
有時候就是會有一些
Their skeletons will leave some fundamental
他們的骨骼會留下來一些基正
just let us know
就是讓我們知道就是
This is Jintun using the ones from Jintun as some building materials
這是金屯用金屯的這個去當一些某一些建材
The most commonly seen is Jintun's
最常看到就是把金屯的
Especially the bones that should be gold are used as bridges
特別是應該是金的骨拿去做橋
There are many records of this
這個記載不少
This is the photo of the golden fish bone of Lanji
這個是藍極的這個金的魚骨的照片
In addition, some people regard it as a good pillar
另外就是還有人把它當作良柱
The most special thing in Zhuang Liangzhu is that there is a photo
當作良柱裡面最特別的就是有一張照片
Let's look at that photo first
這張照片我們先看那張照片
There is a photo in the period of the Republic of China
就是民國時期有一張照片
It is mentioned that there is a magnetic hall in their family
裡面提到他們家族當中有一個磁堂
There is a Wuliang in the middle of the magnetic hall
磁堂當中有一個中間這個烏梁
a string of words written on it
上面寫著一串字
That string of characters is this
那串字是這個
In the 20th year of Qianlong in the Qing Dynasty, the first day of the first lunar month
大清乾隆二十年以駭正月朔
word entry
字入
It was the one that ran into Hong Kong with myself
就是那一條與自己跑進了本港
It is the oracle bone of a sea mound in Hong Kong Harbor
就是港港口的一條海丘的甲骨
used oracle bones to make their Wuliang
用了甲骨去做他們的烏梁
It also has the string of words written on it
上面還寫著那串字
this is very special
這個就非常特別
In fact, there are many records of unscrupulous temples or homes.
其實當作廟或是家裡的無良的記載也不少
don't talk
就不講
There is also a record that Xiaojin was taken as a specimen after being separated from Qianqian.
還有記載講到把小金與隔淺之後拿去做標本
This has come after the Republic of China
這個已經到民國以後
There is probably only one record that I found
記載大概只有我查到就僅有一條
But it is also possible that there are
但是相關的可能這種情況也有
But it's not recorded
但是沒有被記載下來而已
In addition, sometimes it will be displayed in some places
還有就是說有時候會被放在有些地方展示
For example, there are some temples that are most often released
比如說最常被放的就是有一些廟
For example, Xu Yue’s Jianwen Road talks about the water temple in Laizhou, Shandong.
比如說這個許越的建文路裡面就講到山東來州這個地方的水神廟
Saw some big fish skeletons in that place
在那個地方有看到一些大的魚的骨架
In addition, he also said that he used to be in the area of ​​Haizhou Joint Venture Port
另外他還說他曾經在海州聯營港這一帶
I saw that the common people used this fishbone to make old things, etc.
看到老百姓用這個魚骨去做舊等等
This is the vanity of gold
這是虛金的虛
It's the Xu on the mouth
就是那個嘴巴上面的這個許
it's funny
這很搞人更然
It's a photo of Xiyang
是西洋的一個照片
a photo of the west
西方的一個照片
he can take it
他可以拿去
that someone
那個有人
The Chinese have ever taken him that
中國人有曾經把他拿那個
the one above
上面的這個
This thing on the lake
湖叙上面的這個東西
what to do
拿去做什麼
take it to numbers
拿去做數字
This was recorded in the Tang Dynasty
這個在唐代的時候有記載
one more special
還有一個對特別
It's in that Weihaiwei place
是在那個威海衛這個地方
placed at this gate of the park
被放在公園的這個門口
that as a landscape
那當做那個一個造景
let's take a look
我們看一下
That's the one
就是那個
There is a place in Weihaiwei
這個威海衛有個地方
The locals call it Shanjiao Park
那個當地人叫做山腳公園
because it's hilltop
因為它是山腳型的
this is gone now
這個現在已經不見了
Because I used to go to Weihaiwei
因為我曾經去那個威海衛國
to see this place
要看這個地方
this is gone
這個已經沒有了
that mouth this
那個嘴巴的這個
where has been moved
已經被搬到哪裡去了
This is the Republic of China
這是民國的
More than ten years of the Republic of China
民國十幾年
we're coming to conclusions
我們要講結論了
about the time
大概時間差不多
The conclusion is probably that
那結論大概就是說
The vast majority of extant cases are
現存的絕大部分的個案都
The main record is after the middle of the night in the Ming Dynasty
主要的記載度在明代中夜以後
Before the middle of the night in the Ming Dynasty, it was relatively scattered
在明代中夜前就相對比較凌散
that last point
那最後一點而言
Probably from the north bank of the Yangtze Estuary to that
大概是長江口北岸到那個
Zhejiang Lane Shangan
浙江那個巷山桿
that's the one
也就是那個
The coast of Zhoushan Islands
周山群島這一帶的海岸
It is the place where the most gold is mainly cut
是金類主要割遣最多的地方
Hangzhou Bay even has hundreds of
杭州灣甚至有數百條
Records of Jintun Separation
金屯割遣的紀錄
Generally speaking
一般來說
Jintun's size
金屯的尺寸
The size of the cutout is about 10 pieces in length
割遣的尺寸大概長度超過10張
more than a few
以上的還不少
There is a relatively high possibility that it may be virtual gold
可能是虛金的可能性相對較高
and most of what we can now determine
而且大部分我們現在可以判定的
some are smeared gold
有一些是抹香金
gold class leave the world
金類留給世界上
It's this souvenir from our world
就是我們人間的這個紀念品
Actually quite a lot
其實蠻多的
certainly
當然
The most obvious is probably
最明顯的大概就是
The most common is Gouger
最常見的就是谷格
So like I just said
所以就像我剛剛講的
It's going to be used as frozen food, bridge food.
就是會被拿來當作凍糧 橋糧
Or chairs and stools and smart old
或是椅子 凳還有聰明的舊
There are even dug into steel
甚至還有挖成鋼狀的
Those who can raise whales have this
可以養鯨魚的 這個都有
in traditional times
在傳統時代
because there's nothing like a museum or anything
因為沒有像博物館或是什麼
Oceanarium or something like that
海洋館之類的這種
places to collect this skeleton about Jintun
場所來收集這個有關於金屯的骨架
So the most common way
所以最常見的一種方式
is often placed in the square of the temple
就是常常被放在廟宇的廣場
that's about binhai
那有關於這個賓海
Common people, they cut money from Jintun
老百姓他們對於金屯割錢的這個
Explanations are of course full of cultural imagination
解釋當然都充滿了文化的想像
Some of them are mystical
其中就是有一些是神秘主義
I just said this
那這個我剛剛已經講過
That is to say, Dragonsea put this
就是講到海龍網把這個
The bad fish rushed into the army
不乖的魚沖軍
besides
還有
Later it was said about the so-called
後來有關於就所謂的說
It will appear during the Lunar New Year, etc.
潤年的時候會出現等等
later joined together
後來又結合在一起
These actually represent a kind of thinking of human beings.
這些其實都是代表了人類的一種思維
In fact, it has no scientific basis
其實它也並沒有一些科學的依據
The last thing I want to say is that
那最後我要講就是說那個
After the great geographical discovery in the west
西方在那個大在整個地理大發現以後
Actually a lot of that kill goldfish
其實大量的那個捕殺金魚
Actually, and use this goldfish as a good fuel
其實而且用這個金魚來當作很好的燃料
and lubricant
還有潤滑劑
But in China relatively because
但是在中國相對因為
The frequency of goldfish cutting skirts is actually not too high
那種金魚割裙的頻率其實也不是太高
In addition, China except the South China Sea area
再加上中國除了南海這一帶
There is a supplement to this custom
有補金的這個習慣之外
It's the Danmin of the South China Sea
就是南海的淡民
It's a kind of ethnic minority of the sea
就是一種海上的這種族群淡民
they will kill jintun
他們會補殺金屯
except them
除了他們之外
Probably most of them will not take the initiative to go to sea without killing
大概大部分都不會主動的出海不殺
In this process, there can actually be a result
在這個過程當中其實也就可以造成一個結果
It's the kind of poisonous milk that we use in the sea.
就是我們所使用的這種海上的毒乳類的染友
is so relatively less
是這樣對比較少
So some Western scholars say that this is a big difference
所以有西方的學者就說這個是一個很大的差別
This is of course
這個當然也是
Okay, I'll probably report it here, thank you all
好 那大概就報告到這邊 謝謝大家
Don't pay attention to the artistic conception and then don't pay attention to the reality
不要注重意境 然後不注重現實
That's because of this, so it affects everyone and won't do it deliberately.
那是因為這樣子的緣故 所以影響大家不會去刻意進行
detailed records
詳實的記錄
The appearance of goldfish cutting money
金魚割錢的樣子
then come again
然後再過來是
japan for goldfish
日本對於金魚
It seems that there are more records
好像有比較多記錄
Because it is Putin's tradition
因為就是有普京的傳統
Then it was mentioned at the end that
然後剛剛最後有提到說
Danming in southern China has such a culture
中國南方的淡明有這樣的文化
that's curious
那很好奇就是
Is the lightness of southern China the same as that of Japan?
中國南方的淡明是不是跟日本的
Is there any record of communication
有沒有什麼交流的記錄
or mutual cultural influence
或者是互相文化影響的
This related history
這種相關的歷史記錄
and then the third is
然後第三個是
It is recorded that there are
就是記載裡面有
It is mentioned that PVT just now
有提到就是剛剛PVT
one word is
有一個詞是
Everyone thinks it's weird because everyone thinks it's a weird thing
眾以為怪 因為大家覺得是一個怪事
Then or someone feels that it is
然後或者是有人覺得是在
It's the goldfish who's coming to worship
是那個金魚要來拜
Come to Dragon King, I have to swim back again
來龍王 還要再游回去
then or something even a fallen dragon
然後或者是什麼甚至是墮龍
dragon that fell from the sky
天上掉下來的龍
Then I'm curious, so the record inside
那就很好奇 這樣記錄裡面
mostly positive context
主要是以正面的語境偏多
Still more negative context
還是負面的語境偏多
Can positive or negative this be used as a
那正面或負面這個能不能作為一種
Will the current government use it to explain
當時代的政府會不會拿來解釋說
Oh because of the country we govern now
哦 就是因為我們現在治理的國家
very common
很常見
That's why God has images to make auspicious omens
所以才天有意象的讓祥瑞之兆
It's more like a negative
還是比較像是負面的
It is because the emperor of the previous era was married
就是因為他前一個時代的皇帝婚庸
So this happened in the previous era
所以前一個時代才會發生這種
This kind of imaginative thing
這種天有意象的事情
Is it more positive or more negative?
就是是正面比較多還是負面比較多
Can it have a
能不能帶有一種
An explanation of the social atmosphere of that era
對於那個時代的社會氛圍的解釋
Li Chang
李昌
Okay, that's the first question.
好 第一個問題就說那個
I think your question should be certain.
我覺得你的提問應該是有一定的那個
probably because
可能 因為
But we can't actually find real evidence
但是我們實際上找不到真正的證據
Because the Chinese, of course, basically
因為中國人當然基本上來講
He is a literati, he is more interested in art
就是文人他比較是在藝術上
It's more about artistic conception, that's right.
就比較講求意境這是沒有錯的
But we might just have a possibility
不過我們可能就是有一個可能性
Why does this kind of image data remain less
為什麼會造成這種圖像資料留下來比較少
The first is when this happened
第一個就是這個事情發生的時候
possibly local
可能當地的
It is possible to find that gold and pigeons are both
發現這個金與鴿起來都是可能是
fishermen living by the sea
住在海邊的漁民
some local people
當地的一些人
Ordinary people, they may not actually have the ability to do this
普通老百姓他們其實可能沒有這方面的天奔
Said to keep it and draw it
說要把它留下來 畫下來
There are also some possibilities
另外還有一些可能性可以講
It's a fetish. You can't draw a fetish.
就是神物呢 神物是不能畫的
There is a tradition, for example,
就傳統有一種 比如說舉個例子
I've been to that years ago
我一直到那個前幾年
Even three years ago, I went to the mainland for inspection.
就是三年前都還去大陸考察過
I took a camera to take pictures of that god
我拿照相機去照那個神明
The person who took the tour was Zi Zi who didn’t let me take pictures
導覽的人是自子不讓我照的
I just said we don't have this opportunity in Taiwan
我就說我們台灣沒有這個機會
He said we can't do it in this place
他說在這個地方我們不行
That is to say, the local people have been
就是說當地老百姓一直到現在
Even after the Cultural Revolution
雖然已經經過文化大革命了
But they are concerned about God
可是他們對於神這個東西
you can't take pictures of him
你是不能去照他的
can't even draw
甚至不能畫
This may also be to some extent
這個也可能某一個方面來講
It can be explained that like the dragon
可以解釋就是說像被稱為龍的這種
Or fetish they may feel they shouldn't draw it
或是神物他們可能覺得不應該去畫它
This is my conjecture with no evidence
這個是我的推想,沒有證據
The second question is whether this Danming has exchanged experience with Japan in their supplementary funds experience
第二個問題就是說這個淡明跟日本的他們的補金的經驗當中有沒有交流
In fact, I can't see it at all from the literature.
實際上我從文獻上其實完全看不出來
That is to say, this may also be the lack of literature
就是說這個可能也是文獻上的缺乏
In fact, some people say that Danming, a sea group, appeared after the Southern Song Dynasty.
淡明這個海上的族群其實有人說它出現的是在南宋以後
Of course it was possible earlier
當然有可能以前更早
There is a group of people who may have traveled from Fujian to the Gulf of Tonkin in Vietnam.
就是有一批其實他們可能從福建一直到越南東京灣這一代
They are the group of people who live on the water, they don't go on land very much
他們是住在水面上,他們不太上陸地的這一批人
That group of people occasionally
那這一批人他們偶爾
but in some cases
不過在某一些情況下
They go back to make up the money
他們回去補那個金
They don't dare to make up big money
他們補金不敢補大金
They found that tissue shoveled out in some seasons
他們在某一些季節裡面發現那個紙巾被鏟出來
They shoot him with that fish mark
他們就用那個魚標去射他
After shooting him and letting him die at sea
射他之後就讓他在海上死了之後
slow down
慢慢就拖拖拖
drag it to the sand drag it to the sand to untie it
拖到沙岸 拖到沙灘上去把它解
boil after disintegration
解體之後去熬湧
Because after all they need fuel at sea too
因為畢竟他們在海上也很需要燃料
so they are probably
所以他們大概是
but not too many
但是數量不是太多
Records began to appear in the Ming Dynasty
記載開始有出現是在明代
There was a Chongzhou in the Ming Dynasty
明代有一個重州
Fuzhi, a state of political virtue, began to record that
政德重州福治開始記載說
But tomorrow will make up money
但明會補金
Every year, they will replenish paper towels in some seasons
每年他們大概某一些季節會去補紙巾
Because we don't know how the group got here
因為我們不知道這個族群到底是怎麼來的
maybe he's ugly
也許他很難看
It was related to Japan very early on.
很早是跟日本是有關係的
Or stay in Japan for a long time and they are related
或是留久日本他們有關係
But there is absolutely no relevant research
可是完全就是沒有相關的研究
Talking about the relationship between the two ethnic groups
談到說兩個族群之間
Is there an absolute connection?
到底有沒有絕對的關聯性
Even with current affairs that probably lack documentation
即使有大概很欠缺文獻帳的時政
Of course everyone in Japan knows
日本當然大家都知道
Even now there are still people
就是一直到現在還有人
Occasionally go to make up money
偶爾會去補金
So there's a documentary about a bay
所以有紀錄片講到一個海灣
Inside a village bay
一個村子的海灣裡面
After they put him right into that bay
他們把他右進那個海灣之後
intercept it at that estuary
在那個海口把它截住
Then the whole sea is red
接著就整個海面都紅
cruel
比較殘忍
what is the third question
第三個問題是什麼
I just want to know the positive side of the record.
就是想知道記載裡面的正面的
think of me
對我想起來
In fact, I just mentioned the first earliest record
其實剛剛講到第一條最早的記載
It is the record of the Han Dynasty
是那個漢代的記載
He is recorded in five elements
裡面他是被記載五行字的
It is recorded in it that when those phenomena appeared
在裡面記載說那幾個現象出現的時候
It's negative, it's the heavenly scene
是負面的 就是那個上天事景
It's the emperor, you didn't do well
就是皇帝你做得不好
you can't handle some things
你有些事情處置不好
So that day has imagery
所以那個天有意象
This fetish was rushed up
這個神物就被衝上來
This is asking the emperor to recruit himself
這個就是要求皇帝要下招罪己
There are also adjustments to be made in terms of governance
還有就施政上面要進行調整
Later, it was extensively documented
後來就是在大量記載
on the local word
在地方字上面
It is also often recorded in the will
也常常把它記載在在意志裡面
in the will of course
在意志裡面當然
You start with the words that will
你就從那個在意志這幾個詞
I know it's a kind of care
就知道它是一種在意
It thinks that the appearance of this thing is not a good thing
它認為這個東西出現不是好事情
In addition, there are some literatures that say
再加上有一些文獻裡面講到說
I didn't just talk about
我剛剛不是講到
that is to say some talk is to say
就是說有些講到就是說
as long as this kind of thing appears
只要這種東西出現
That reporter has a strong wind
那記者就有大風
Then we know that the southeast also sea
那我們知道東南也海
Especially in Zhejiang and Fujian
特別是浙江福建這一帶
The most common occurrence is
最常出現的就是
What is the so-called big front behind the so-called big front
所謂的大鋒 後面的所謂大鋒是什麼
It's a typhoon or a big cyclone
就是颱風 或是有大的氣旋
Although not to the typhoon level
雖然沒有到颱風等級
But it will make the whole coast
可是它會讓這個整個沿海
Great changes in the weather began
就開始出現氣象的很大的變化
So I saw an actual record in Zhejiang
所以浙江我看到實際的一個記載
They said that as long as they saw the sea station
他們就講到說只要看到海駐
is Haiti
就是海地
when it rolls and bounces like this on the sea
它在海面上這樣翻滾彈跳的時候
Everyone should be careful and start to be on guard
大家就要小心了 開始要防備
So in other words, fishermen off the coast
所以也就是說在沿海的漁民
in the eyes of ordinary people
跟普通老百姓的眼裡
If something like this happens, I'm afraid it will bring disaster.
這種東西出現恐怕就是會帶來災難
There aren't too many positive records.
那正面記載的其實不是太多
It is usually considered strange that this appears
通常會認為這個出現很奇怪
In fact, it includes one of the teasing disasters
其實包括撩災之一裡面
send it to this kind of thing, it will
都寄到這種東西 就會
just show that it's not
就顯示就是說它不是
That is to say, in ancient times
也就是說在古代來講
The rating is not particularly high
評率不是特別的高
Because if something like this happens
因為這種東西如果有出現的話
Chinese people are actually curious
中國人其實很好奇
Most will take it down
大部分都會把它記下來
but miscellaneous
但是雜七雜八
Of course, that is why after the Ming Dynasty there were more
當然就是為什麼明代以後開始比較多
It is because there are more written materials left than before
就是因為留下來的文字材料要比以前多
So there are relatively many records
所以記載相對比較多
It may have been recorded before
以前可能有記載
But after a while some books were passed on privately
但是過一段時間以後有些書私傳了
Or there are some official files
或是有一些官方檔案
Maybe he also reported to be an official
可能他也報到當官方去了
but did not stay
可是沒有留下來
So generally speaking
所以總體來講就是說
not too much positive
正面的不太多
usually taken as an image
通常會當做一種意象
not a good sign
不是好現象
right
對
Then we thank the teacher for bringing us today
那我們今天就謝謝老師帶來
our wonderful speeches
我們精采的演講
Thanks
謝謝
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝